Jean Day Zallinger Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Jean Day Zallinger Papers.
undated, 1969-1994.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Zallinger, Jean Day.
12 linear feet.
Jean Day Zallinger was born in February 1918, in Boston, Mass. She attended the Massachusetts College of Art and received a B.F.A. from the Yale School of Fine Arts in 1942. Mrs. Zallinger has illustrated numerous children's books, mainly non-fictional works about animals and plants, including such titles as Biography of a Leaf, Discovering What Earthworms Do, The Earliest Americans, and Sea Creatures Do Amazing Things.
MSS19970077
Biography
Jean Day Zallinger was born in February 1918, in Boston, Mass. She attended the Massachusetts College of Art and received a B.F.A. from the Yale School of Fine Arts in 1942. She married Rudolph Franz Zallinger (also an artist) in 1941. She spent most of her career living in North Haven, Connecticut, and teaching at the Paier School of Art in Hamden, Connecticut. Mrs. Zallinger has illustrated numerous children's books, mainly non-fictional works about animals and plants, including such titles as Biography of a Leaf, Discovering What Earthworms Do, The Earliest Americans, and Sea Creatures Do Amazing Things.
Illustrator
Alligators and Crocodiles, undated.
Jean C. George, The Moon of the Owls, Crowell, 1967.
Seymour Simon, Discovering What Earthworms Do, McGraw-Hill, 1969.
Lee Ford, Water Boatman's Journey, Seabury Press, 1969.
Ross E. Hutchins, The Mayfly, Addison-Wesley, 1970.
Burke Davis, Biography of a Leaf, Putnam, 1972.
Lisbeth Zappler, Natural History of the Tail, Doubleday, 1972.
Francine Jacobs, Sea Turtles, Morrow, 1972.
Mary Adrian, Secret Neigbors, Holiday House, 1972.
Alice L. Hopf, Biography of an Armadillo, Putnam, 1975.
Herbert H. Wong, My Snail, Addison-Wesley, 1976.
Gladys P. Conklin, I Watch Flies, Holiday House, 1977.
Francine Jacobs, Sounds in the Sea, Morrow, 1977.
Herbert S. Zim, Little Cats, Morrow, 1978.
Herbert S. Zim, Your Skin, Morrow, 1979.
Alice L. Hopf, Biography of a Komodo Dragon, Putnam, 1981.
Arthur Myers, Sea Creatures Do Amazing Things, Random House, 1981.
Caroline Arnold, Sex Hormones: Why Males and Females are Different, Morrow, 1981.
Helen R. Sattler, Baby Dinosaurs, Lothrop, Lee & Shepard, 1984.
Daniel Cohen, Dinosaurs, Doubleday, 1986.
Helen R. Sattler, Sharks, the Super Fish, Lothrop, Lee & Shepard, 1986.
Helen R. Sattler, Whales, The Nomads of the Sea, Lothrop, Lee & Shepard, 1987.
Helen R. Sattler, The Book of Eagles, Lothrop, Lee & Shepard, 1989.
Rita G. Gelman, Monsters of the Sea, Brown, 1990.
Myra C. Livingston, Poems for Brothers and Sisters, Holiday House, 1991.
Helen R. Sattler, The Earliest Americans, Houghton-Mifflin, 1993.
Helen R. Sattler, The Book of North American Owls, Clarion Books, 1994.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of Ms. Zallinger's original artwork for more than 20 books. In addition to the original art, collection contains a number of book dummies, publisher's proofs, and print editions for a few of the titles.
NOTE: One printed copy of Whales, Nomads of the Sea (CLC D382) and 2 printed copies of Poems for Brothers, Poems for Sisters (CLC C1917) were removed from the collection for cataloging.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of children's literature and associated artwork. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Children's literature, American—20th century.; Children's literature—Illustrations.
Document Types:
Artwork.; Print materials.; Manuscripts.
Occupations:
Illustrator.; Artist.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
All materials donated to the Dodd Center by Jean Day Zallinger. A small donation was made in 1992, but most of the collection was donated in 1997.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Books, 1969-1994
  - Alligators and Crocodiles, undated
    - line art (31 pcs.), notes and copies (6 pcs.) (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Baby Dinosaurs, Helen R. Sattler, 1984
    - MS, notes, galley copies, color galley (Box 8:, Folder 56)
  - Biography of a Komodo Dragon, Alice L. Hopf, 1981
    - dummy w/ text and sketches (Box 2:, Folder 12A)
    - jacket (4 pcs.), original art for pp. 1-29, (15 pcs.) (Box 2:, Folder 12B)
    - original art for pp. 31-64, (18 pcs.) (Box 2:, Folder 12C)
  - Biography of a Leaf, Burke Davis, 1972
    - dummy w/ text and sketches (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - original art pp. 2-21, (10 pcs.) (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - original art pp. 22-47, (13 pcs.) (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Biography of an Armadillo, Alice L. Hopf, 1975
    - dummy w/ sketches, (34 pcs.) (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - The Book of Eagles, Helen R. Sattler, 1989
    - dummy with text and sketches (Box 4:, Folder 26)
    - color proofs for pp. 1-64 (Box 4:, Folder 27)
    - first color proofs (50 pcs.), jacket proof (Box 4:, Folder 28)
    - original color art (48 pcs.), includes variant color art for p. 47 (Box 4:, Folder 29)
    - original art for cover, pp. 14-15, 18-19, 22-23, large color proof of frontispiece (Box 4:, Folder 30)
  - The Book of North American Owls, Helen R. Sattler, 1995
    - color proofs, (29 pcs.) (Box 4:, Folder 22)
  - Dinosaurs, Daniel Cohen, 1986
    - full color art pp. 16-17, 36-37, (2 pcs.) (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Discovering What Earthworms Do, a book on frogs (?), And 1 pc. color art for a book on monkeys
  - The Earliest Americans, Helen R. Sattler, 1993
    - MS, notes with some sketches (Box 3:, Folder 16)
    - 2 sets of proofs, jacket proof (Box 3:, Folder 17)
    - dummy with text and sketches (Box 3:, Folder 18)
    - proofs (7 pcs.), original art for pp. 10-13, 16-29, 36-37 (10 pcs.) (Box 3:, Folder 19)
    - original art for pp. 38-39, 42-45, 48-57, 60-67, (12 pcs.) (Box 3:, Folder 20)
    - original art for pp. 68-75, 80-81, 84-93, 96-97, (11 pcs.) (Box 3:, Folder 21)
  - I Watch Flies, Gladys P. Conklin, 1977
    - jacket separations, (3 pcs) (Box 6:, Folder 47)
  - Little Cats, Herbert S. Zim, 1978
    - dummy, preliminary art, (31 pcs.) (Box 8:, Folder 62)
    - original art for pp. 1 (blank), 3, 6-9, 12-15, 18-19, 22-23, (8 pcs.) (Box 8:, Folder 63)
    - original art for pp. 30-35, 38-47, (8 pcs.) (Box 8:, Folder 64)
    - original art for pp. 50-63, (7 pcs.) (Box 8:, Folder 65)
  - The Mayfly, Ross E. Hutchins, 1970
    - separations, (16 pcs.) (Box 2:, Folder 10)
  - Monsters of the Sea, Rita G. Gelman, 1990
    - Color Proof Set, dummy with text and sketches, original art for jacket (Box 2:, Folder 14)
    - text overlays (4 pcs.), original art for pp. 2-11, 14-23, 26-31 (13 pcs.) (Box 2:, Folder 15)
  - The Moon of the Owls, Jean C. George, 1967
    - dummy w/ corrections (Box 8:, Folder 59)
    - original line art, (16 pcs.) (Box 8:, Folder 60)
    - preliminary jacket (Box 8:, Folder 61)
    - Jacket Art - (16 total pcs.) includes art for, ca. 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 13)
  - My Snail, Herbert H. Wong, 1976
    - jacket proof (1 pc.), separations (23 pcs.) (Box 2:, Folder 11)
  - The Natural History of the Tail, Lisbeth Zappler, 1972
    - original art for pp. 1, 5-16, (8 pcs.) (Box 7:, Folder 48)
    - original art for pp. 16-29, (7 pcs.) (Box 7:, Folder 49)
    - original art for pp. 30-41, (8 pcs.) (Box 7:, Folder 50)
    - original art for pp. 42-52, (8 pcs.) (Box 7:, Folder 51)
    - original art for pp. 53, 55-57, 60-64, (7 pcs.) (Box 7:, Folder 52)
    - dummy (pt I, 14 pcs.) (Box 7:, Folder 53)
    - dummy (pt. II, 20 pcs.) (Box 7:, Folder 54)
  - Poems for Brothers and Sisters, Myra C. Livingston, 1991
    - dummy with text and sketches (Box 4:, Folder 24)
    - original art, (18 pcs.) (Box 4:, Folder 25)
  - Sea Creatures Do Amazing Things, Arthur Myers, 1981
    - proofs, jacket proofs (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - layout/dummy sheets, (33 pcs.) (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - line art, (27 pcs.) (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Sea Turtles, Francine Jacobs, 1972
    - pencil finishes, (46 pcs.) (Box 8:, Folder 55)
  - Secret Neighbors, Mary Adrian, 1972
    - original line art, (18 pcs.) (Box 8:, Folder 57)
  - Sex Hormones: Why Males and Females are Different, Caroline Arnold, 1981
    - jacket art and proof, (2 pcs.) (Box 4:, Folder 23)
  - Sharks, the Super Fish, Helen R. Sattler, 1986
    - preliminary dummy with line art sketches (Box 5:, Folder 31)
    - preliminary text paste-up (partial) (Box 5:, Folder 32)
    - proof set with jacket proof (Box 5:, Folder 33)
    - line art for pp. 35-49, (23 pcs.) (Box 5:, Folder 34)
    - line art for pp. 50-59, (15 pcs.) (Box 5:, Folder 35)
    - line art for pp. 60-76, (29 pcs.) (Box 5:, Folder 36)
    - line art for pp. 77-93, (26 pcs.) (Box 5:, Folder 37)
    - original art for pp. 2-34, 44-45, 90-91, (21 pcs.) (Box 5:, Folder 38)
  - Sounds in the Sea, Francine Jacobs, 1977
    - original line art, (26 pcs.) (Box 8:, Folder 58)
  - Water Boatman's Journey, Lee Ford, 1969
    - jacket proof, illustration copies w/ text paste-ins, (21 total pcs.) (Box 6:, Folder 44)
    - separations for jacket, pp. 1-13 (Box 6:, Folder 45)
    - separations for pp. 14-32 (Box 6:, Folder 46)
  - Whales, The Nomads of the Sea, Helen R. Sattler, 1987
    - dummy with text and sketches (pt. I of dummy) (Box 5:, Folder 39)
    - dummy, pt. II (Box 5:, Folder 40)
    - glossary line art for pp. 54-115, (41 pcs.) (Box 5:, Folder 41)
    - color jacket art (1 pc.), dummy with sketches (34 pcs.) (Box 5:, Folder 42)
    - original art, (42 pcs.) (Box 5:, Folder 43)
  - Your Skin, Herbert S. Zim, 1979
    - line art for jacket, pp. 3-15, (8 pcs.) (Box 9:, Folder 66)
    - line art for pp. 16-17, 20-29, 32-33, (7 pcs.) (Box 9:, Folder 67)
    - line art for pp. 34-51, (9 pcs.) (Box 9:, Folder 68)
    - line art for pp. 52-57, 60, 63, (5 pcs.) (Box 9:, Folder 69)